so for the last portion of this first lecture module
그래서 이 첫 번째 강의 모듈의 마지막 부분에서
i'd like to come back to a question that i asked earlier how do we build intelligent machines
저는 이전에 우리가 어떻게 지능형 기계를 만들 수 있는지 물었던 질문으로 돌아가고 싶습니다.
if we really want to think about this problem kind of as engineers if we forget everything that we know about learning reinforcement learning and so on
우리가 강화 학습 등 학습에 대해 알고 있는 모든 것을 잊어버리고 엔지니어와 같이 이 문제에 대해 정말로 생각한다면
and you have to build an intelligent machine where would you start
어디서부터 시작해서 지능형 기계를 구축해야 할까요.
maybe a very logical place to start is to think about all of the things that the brain has to do the human brain
아마도 매우 논리적인 출발점은 인간의 뇌에서 하는 모든 일에 대해 생각하는 것입니다
think of them as independent modules
그것들을 독립적인 모듈로 생각하십시오.
and try to program in modules that do that breaking up the brain into individual parts and thinking about their function is a very old study and you know that goes back before even the modern cientific era
뇌를 개별 부분으로 분해하고 그 기능에 대해 생각하는 것은 아주 오래된 연구이며 현대 과학 시대 이전으로 거슬러 올라가는 것을 수행하는 모듈을 프로그래밍 할 수 있습니다.
of course today's understanding is a little more sophisticated than it was in the 19th century
물론 오늘날의 이해는 19세기보다 조금 더 정교합니다.
but there's still a lot of work trying to anatomically chop up the brain into parts with different functions
하지만 해부학적으로 뇌를 다양한 기능을 가진 부분으로 자르기 위해 많은 노력이 필요합니다.
so then it's very tempting as an engineer to think about building individual computer components to reproduce those functions
따라서 엔지니어로서 이러한 기능을 재현하기 위해 개별 컴퓨터 구성 요소를 구축하는 것에 대해 생각하는 것은 매우 유혹적입니다.
but this quickly becomes very difficult
그러나 이것은 곧 매우 어려워집니다.
because there are a lot of these parts implementing each of them is very hard
이러한 부분이 많기 때문에 각각을 구현하는 것은 매우 어렵습니다.
and implementing all of them might require an inordinate amount of work
그리고 그것들을 모두 구현하려면 엄청난 양의 작업이 필요할 수 있습니다.
what if we instead consider whether learning could be seen as the basis of intelligence
대신 학습이 지능의 기초로 간주될 수 있는지 고려한다면 어떨까요?
i'm going to make an argument for why this might be true this is not by any means a widely accepted or universally accepted opinion
나는 이것이 사실일 수 있는 이유에 대해 논증할 것입니다. 이것은 결코 널리 받아 들여지거나 보편적으로 받아 들여지는 의견이 아닙니다.
but perhaps you know we can just entertain that notion and see where it leads us
하지만 아마도 당신은 우리가 그 개념을 즐겁게 할 수 있고 그것이 우리를 어디로 이끄는지 알 수 있다는 것을 알고 있을 것입니다.
one way we could argue for this notion is to say well there are some things that we can all do like walking
우리가 이 개념을 주장할 수 있는 한 가지 방법은 우리 모두가 걷기처럼 할 수 있는 몇 가지가 있다고 말하는 것입니다.
but there are some other things that clearly we have to learn
하지만 분명히 우리가 배워야 할 몇 가지 다른 것들이 있습니다.
because there's no way that humans could through evolution be prepared for things like driving a car
인간이 진화를 통해 차를 운전하는 것과 같은 일에 대비할 수 있는 방법이 없기 때문입니다.
cars weren't around when we evolved
우리가 진화했을 때 자동차는 주변에 없었습니다.
so the argument here would be that we can learn a huge variety of things
제가 하고자 하는 말은 우리가 엄청나게 다양한 것들을 배울 수 있다는 것입니다.
so that second category some things we can only learn it's a very large category there's a huge variety of things we can learn
우리가 배울 수 있는 두 번째 범주는 매우 큰 범주입니다. 우리가 배울 수 있는 것은 매우 다양합니다.
including extremely difficult things
매우 어려운 일을 포함합니다.
and while there might be some things that we could argue or innate the range of things we can learn is so broad that perhaps it basically captures everything that we care about
우리가 논쟁하거나 타고난 것들이 있을 수 있지만 우리가 배울 수 있는 것의 범위는 너무 광범위하여 기본적으로 우리가 관심 있는 모든 것을 포착할 수 있습니다.
and those things that are innate we could have learned them also if they weren't an age to begin with
그리고 선천적인 것들은 시작할 나이가 아니었어도 배울 수 있었을 것입니다.
so therefore our learning mechanisms are likely powerful enough to do basically everything that we associate with intelligence
따라서 우리의 학습 메커니즘은 기본적으로 우리가 지능과 연관시키는 모든 것을 할 수 있을 만큼 충분히 강력합니다.
maybe you agree or disagree with this notion but if you humor this notion for a second
이 개념에 동의하거나 동의하지 않을 수도 있지만 잠시 이 개념을 유머러스하게 표현한다면
we could think about how we'd use it to refine our plan for building intelligence
인텔리전스를 구축하기 위한 계획을 구체화하기 위해 이를 어떻게 사용할지 생각할 수 있습니다.
now we could simply take this recipe and use it to instead of designing the functionality of each module instead design a learning algorithm for each module so we say well okay
이제 우리는 이 레시피를 사용하여 각 모듈의 기능을 설계하는 대신 각 모듈에 대한 학습 알고리즘을 설계하여 괜찮다고 말할 수 있습니다.
we're not going to implement the visual cortex of the motor cortex by hand
우리는 손으로 운동 피질의 시각 피질을 구현하지 않을 것입니다
what we'll instead implement is a learning algorithm for the visual cortex
대신 우리가 구현할 것은 시각 피질에 대한 학습 알고리즘입니다.
and a separate algorithm for the motor cortex
운동 피질에 대한 별도의 알고리즘입니다.
this kind of thing was a dominant way of thinking about machine learning in the 90s and early 2000s
이런 종류의 것은 90년대와 2000년대 초반에 기계 학습에 대한 지배적인 사고 방식이었습니다.
but what if we hypothesize that perhaps there's a single flexible algorithm that can do all of these things
하지만 이 모든 작업을 수행할 수 있는 유연한 단일 알고리즘이 있다고 가정하면 어떨까요?
perhaps not only is learning the basis of intelligence
아마도 지능의 기초를 배우는 것뿐만 아니라
but instead but in fact learning with a single powerful algorithm as the basis of intelligence
대신에 지능의 기초로서 하나의 강력한 알고리즘을 사용하여 실제로 학습합니다.
it's a very provocative notion but it's also a very appealing one
그것은 매우 도발적인 개념이지만 또한 매우 매력적인 개념이기도 합니다.
because it suggests that we could save ourselves a lot of work
많은 작업을 절약할 수 있음을 암시하기 때문입니다.
instead of designing a separate algorithm for each module we simply design one algorithm that is broad enough and flexible enough to acquire all these capabilities
각 모듈에 대해 별도의 알고리즘을 설계하는 대신 이러한 모든 기능을 획득할 수 있을 만큼 충분히 광범위하고 유연한 하나의 알고리즘을 설계하기만 하면 됩니다.
and there is a bit of evidence a bit of circumstantial evidence to suggest that something like this might in fact be close to what's going on in the real brain
그리고 이와 같은 것이 실제로 실제 뇌에서 일어나는 일과 비슷할 수 있음을 시사하는 약간의 증거가 있습니다.
these are these pieces of evidence they all have the general flavor of illustrating some degree of flexibility that is unusual or unexpected
이것들은 모두 비정상적이거나 예상치 못한 어느 정도의 유연성을 설명하는 일반적인 풍미를 가지고 있는 이러한 증거입니다.
for instance you could acquire this degree of visual acuity by using your tongue you could take a camera with electrodes attached to it
예를 들어 혀를 사용하여 이 정도의 시력을 얻을 수 있습니다. 전극이 부착된 카메라를 찍을 수 있습니다.
and place those electrodes on your tongue
그리고 그 전극을 혀에 댑니다.
and then close your eyes
그리고 눈을 감죠.
or if you're blind try to use your tongue to see
또는 눈이 먼 경우 혀를 사용하여 볼 수 있습니다.
and then perform some tests of visual acuity
그런 다음 몇 가지 시력 테스트를 수행합니다.
and you will in fact with a fair bit of practice acquire degree of visual acuity with your tongue
그리고 실제로 약간의 연습으로 혀로 어느 정도의 시력을 얻게 될 것입니다.
a more extreme experiment this is sometimes referred to as the thera rewiring experiment was performed on animals on fairness where the ferret's optic nerve was disconnected from the visual cortex and reconnected to the auditory cortex surgically when the fair was very very young
좀 더 극단적인 실험이라고 합니다. 공정하게 동물을 대상으로 한 더 극단적인 실험은 아주 어렸을 때 흰 족제비의 시신경이 시각 피질에서 분리되었다가 청각 피질에 외과적으로 다시 연결되었습니다.
then the ferret grew up
그런 다음 페럿이 자랐습니다.
and over the course of its development
그리고 성장 과정에서
it actually recovered a degree of visual acuity
실제로 시력을 어느 정도 회복했습니다.
which means that its auditory cortex was essentially learning how to see
이것은 청각 피질이 본질적으로 보는 법을 배우고 있음을 의미합니다.
so if different sensor cortexes can be repurposed to perform each other's jobs
따라서 서로 다른 센서 피질을 용도 변경하여 서로의 작업을 수행할 수 있다면
perhaps in some sense they're all implementing the same flexible algorithm
어떤 의미에서 그들은 모두 동일한 유연한 알고리즘을 구현하고 있습니다.
we could take this idea even further
우리는 이 아이디어를 더 발전시킬 수 있습니다
and hypothesize that not only sensory cortices
감각 피질뿐만 아니라
but a lot of the functionality of the brain could in fact be performed by a single flexible algorithm
그러나 실제로는 하나의 유연한 알고리즘으로 두뇌의 많은 기능을 수행할 수 있습니다.
we don't know if this is true but it's a very appealing notion
이것이 사실인지는 모르지만 매우 매력적인 개념입니다.
if in fact this is true we could ask what kind of algorithm could it be
이것이 사실이라면 어떤 종류의 알고리즘이 될 수 있는지 물어볼 수 있습니다.
what must the single algorithm be able to do
단일 알고리즘이 수행할 수 있어야 하는 것은 무엇일까요?
it has to be able to interpret rich sensory inputs it has to deal with complex rich open world problems
풍부한 감각 입력을 해석할 수 있어야 하고 복잡하고 풍부한 오픈 월드 문제를 처리해야 합니다.
and it has to choose complex actions which means it has to reason about decision making and control where have we seen that before well these are the two parts of deep reinforcement learning
복잡한 행동을 선택해야 합니다. 이는 의사 결정에 대해 추론하고 제어해야 한다는 것을 의미합니다.
the deep deals with handling complex open world inputs and the reinforcement learning provides the formalism for decision making and control
복잡한 개방형 세계 입력을 처리하고 강화 학습은 의사 결정 및 제어를 위한 형식을 제공합니다.
and in fact there is again some circumstantial evidence that both deep learning and reinforcement learning at least individually provide some sensible model of how the brain processes information
그리고 사실 딥 러닝과 강화 학습 모두 적어도 개별적으로 뇌가 정보를 처리하는 방식에 대한 합리적인 모델을 제공한다는 정황 증거가 있습니다.
so this is a an older paper that's about a decade old at this point called unsupervised learning models of primer of primary cortical receptor fields and receptor field plasticity that tries to analyze the kind of features that are known to exist in the brain
그래서 이것은 뇌에 존재하는 것으로 알려진 종류의 특징을 분석하려고 시도하는 프라이머리 피질 수용체 필드 및 수용체 필드 가소성의 감독되지 않은 학습 모델이라고 불리는 이 시점에서 약 10년 된 오래된 논문입니다.
and compares them to the kind of features that are observed in primate sensor corpses for example they take a simple stimuli like the these kind of you know grading type stimuli which are known to stimulate individual uh receptive fields in the visual cortex
그리고 그것들을 영장류의 센서 시체에서 관찰되는 특징의 종류와 비교합니다. 예를 들어 그들은 시각 피질의 개별 수용장을 자극하는 것으로 알려진 등급 유형 자극과 같은 간단한 자극을 받습니다.
and they analyze the kind of features that are learned from these stimuli by deep neural networks
그리고 그들은 심층 신경망에 의해 이러한 자극으로부터 학습된 특징의 종류를 분석합니다.
and then they compare the statistics of those features to features that are known to exist in the primate visual cortex from experiments on monkeys
그런 다음 그들은 그 특징의 통계를 원숭이 실험에서 영장류 시각 피질에 존재하는 것으로 알려진 특징과 비교합니다.
they do a similar experiment on auditory features so they expose a deep neural network to a range of auditory stimuli look at the statistics of the features that emerge and again compare those to the statistics of features in the brain
그들은 청각 기능에 대해 유사한 실험을 수행하여 심층 신경망을 다양한 청각 자극에 노출시킵니다. 나타나는 기능의 통계를 보고 이를 다시 뇌의 기능 통계와 비교합니다.
and they even have kind of a funny experiment on the sense of touch where they take human subjects they have them manipulate an object with a glove that's been dusted with some white dust
그리고 그들은 촉각에 대한 재미있는 실험을 했습니다. 인간 대상을 잡고 흰 먼지를 뿌린 장갑으로 물체를 조작하게 했습니다.
and they use where the dust was deposited on the glove to train a deep neural network to essentially represent touch sensing features
그리고 그들은 장갑에 먼지가 쌓인 곳을 사용하여 본질적으로 터치 감지 기능을 나타내도록 심층 신경망을 훈련시킵니다.
and they compare them to features that are known to exist from experiments on monkeys where a monkey's hand is placed on a drum with indentations
그리고 그들은 원숭이의 손이 움푹 들어간 고막에 놓이는 원숭이에 대한 실험에서 존재하는 것으로 알려진 특징과 비교합니다.
which rotates and then the monkey sense of touch is recorded from neurons in its brain and again they compare the statistics of these features
회전한 다음 원숭이의 촉각이 뇌의 뉴런에서 기록되고 다시 이 기능의 통계를 비교합니다.
and find that the neural network learn features with similar statistics
신경망이 유사한 통계를 가진 기능을 학습하는지 확인합니다.
now there are a few conclusions we might draw from these experiments
이제 이러한 실험에서 도출할 수 있는 몇 가지 결론이 있습니다.
for example we might conclude that the deep neural network it works the same way the brain works
예를 들어 우리는 심층 신경망이 뇌가 작동하는 것과 같은 방식으로 작동한다고 결론을 내릴 수 있습니다.
but i think there's actually a more simple explanation
하지만 실제로는 더 간단한 설명이 있다고 생각합니다
it's probably not about the deep neural network per se
그것은 아마도 심층 신경망 자체에 관한 것이 아닐 것입니다.
it's probably about the observation that any large heavily overparameterized model will discover features with these statistics
과적합 된 큰 모델이 이러한 통계를 사용하여 기능을 발견할 것이라는 관찰에 관한 것입니다.
because they're just the right features for this data
이 데이터에 딱 맞는 기능이기 때문입니다.
so the features in some sense are perhaps a property of the data itself
따라서 어떤 의미에서 기능은 데이터 자체의 속성일 수 있습니다.
and a powerful enough model regardless of its internal design would acquire those features because they're the right ones
내부 디자인에 관계없이 충분히 강력한 모델은 올바른 기능이기 때문에 이러한 기능을 획득할 것입니다.
there's also quite a bit of evidence in favor of reinforcement learning as a model of how the brain learns
또한 뇌가 학습하는 방법의 모델로서 강화 학습에 찬성하는 증거가 꽤 있습니다.
and in fact reinforced learning was studied in psychology and neuroscience long before it was a field of studying computer science
그리고 사실 강화 학습은 컴퓨터 과학을 연구하는 분야가 되기 훨씬 전에 심리학과 신경 과학에서 연구되었습니다.
so percepts that anticipate reward become associated with similar firing patterns as the reward itself this is a known observation
예상 보상이 보상 자체와 유사한 발사 패턴과 연관된다는 것을 인식합니다. 이것은 알려진 관찰입니다.
sometimes referred to as spectrum dependent plasticity
때로는 스펙트럼 의존적 가소성이라고도 합니다.
the basal ganglia appears to be related to the reward system in the brain
기저핵은 뇌의 보상 시스템과 관련이 있는 것으로 보입니다.
and model 3rl like adaptation is often a good fit for experimental data of animal adaptation but not always
적응과 같은 모델 3rl은 종종 동물 적응의 실험 데이터에 적합하지만 항상 그런 것은 아닙니다.
all right so we might conclude from this i for some client that if in fact there is a single flexible algorithm that can acquire the broad range of behaviors that we associate with human intelligence
좋습니다. 그래서 우리는 어떤 고객을 위해 이것으로부터 결론을 내릴 수 있습니다. 실제로 우리가 인간 지능과 연관시키는 광범위한 행동을 획득할 수 있는 유연한 단일 알고리즘이 있다면
that algorithm perhaps ought to look a little bit like a reinforcement learning algorithm
그 알고리즘은 아마도 강화 학습 알고리즘처럼 보일 것입니다.
and perhaps equipped with large high-capacity representations like deep models
그리고 아마도 딥 모델과 같은 대용량 표현을 갖추고 있을 것입니다.
so then we could say well what can deep learning and rl do well now
그러면 딥 러닝과 rl이 지금 잘할 수 있는 것이 무엇인지 잘 말할 수 있습니다.
basically how close are we to that
기본적으로 우리는 그것에 얼마나 가까이 왔을까요?
and what seems to be missing
그리고 무엇이 부족할까요?
well current deep reinforcement learning algorithms are pretty good at somethings
현재의 심층 강화 학습 알고리즘은 어떤 것에는 꽤 능숙합니다.
they're good at acquiring a high degree of proficiency
그것은 높은 수준의 기술을 습득하거나
and domains governed by simple known rules like board games and video games
보드 게임 및 비디오 게임과 같이 알려진 간단한 규칙이 적용되는 도메인에 능숙합니다.
they're good at learning simple skills with raw sensory input
그것은 원시 감각 입력으로 간단한 기술을 배우는 데 능숙합니다.
given enough experience
충분한 경험을 준다면요
and they're pretty good at learning to imitate given enough human-provided expert behavior
그리고 그들은 충분히 인간이 제공한 전문가 행동을 모방하는 법을 배우는 데 능숙합니다.
but they still fall short in a few very important ways compared to human intelligence or even animal intelligence
그러나 그들은 여전히 인간 지능이나 동물 지능에 비해 몇 가지 매우 중요한 면에서 부족합니다.
humans can learn incredibly quickly
인간은 엄청나게 빨리 배울 수 있습니다
deep reinforcement learning algorithms are not usually known for their efficiency
심층 강화 학습 알고리즘은 일반적으로 효율성으로 알려져 있지 않습니다.
they usually require a very large amount of experience
그것은 일반적으로 매우 많은 경험을 필요로 합니다
and it may be because humans are very good at reusing past knowledge
인간이 과거 지식을 매우 잘 활용하기 때문일 수 있습니다.
so humans can adapt quickly
그래서 인간은 빠르게 적응할 수 있습니다.
for instance this is a commonly done motor control experiment where a person moves a sliver
예를 들어 이것은 사람이 나무 조각을 움직이는 일반적으로 수행되는 운동 제어 실험입니다.
a perturbation is introduced requiring the person to react
사람이 반응해야 하는 방해가 생깁니다.
and then the experimenter measures how many trials a human needs to learn how to overcome any perturbation introduced by the sliver in just a couple of trials
그런 다음 실험자는 인간이 몇 번의 시도에서 나무 조각에 가해진 방해를 극복하는 방법을 배우기 위해 얼마나 많은 시도를 해야 하는지 측정합니다.
but chances are humans aren't learning entirely from scratch they have past experience with physical manipulation moving their bodies and with responding to perturbation forces
그러나 인간은 신체를 움직이는 물리적 조작과 방해의 힘에 반응하는 과거 경험이 있는 처음부터 완전히 배우지 않을 가능성이 있습니다.
transfer learning in deep rl is still an open problem
심층 강화학습에서의 전이 학습은 여전히 미해결 문제입니다.
but its goal is to essentially address this capability
그러나 목표는 본질적으로 이 기능을 구현하는 것입니다.
it's also often not clear in reality what the reward function should be
또한 실제로는 보상 기능이 무엇인지 명확하지 않은 경우가 많습니다.
so in classical reinforcement learning we typically assume the reward function is known and it's correct but in the real world it's far less clear
그래서 고전적인 강화 학습에서 우리는 일반적으로 보상 함수가 알려져 있고 정확하다고 가정하지만 실제 세계에서는 훨씬 덜 명확합니다.
it's also not clear what the role of prediction should be so should we learn by modeling the entire world and then planning through that model
또한 예측의 역할이 무엇인지 명확하지 않으므로 전 세계를 모델링한 다음 해당 모델을 통해 계획하여 학습해야 합니다.
or should we learn directly from trial and error or should
아니면 시행착오를 통해 직접 배워야 할까요?
we do a little bit of both
아니면 둘 다 조금 해야 합니까
but to sum all this up
하지만 이 모든 것을 요약하자면
one of the things that deep reinforcement learning could potentially offer us is a way to think about the acquisition of intelligence in a more unified algorithmic way without having to think about designing individual algorithms or individual modules
심층 강화 학습이 우리에게 잠재적으로 제공할 수 있는 것 중 하나는 개별 알고리즘이나 개별 모듈을 설계할 필요 없이 보다 통합된 알고리즘 방식으로 지능 획득에 대해 생각할 수 있는 방법입니다.
but this is not by any means a new idea going from this kind of modular very complex model to a simple learning driven model is something that is in some sense as old as computer science itself
그러나 이것은 이러한 종류의 매우 복잡한 모듈식 모델에서 단순한 학습 주도 모델로 가는 새로운 아이디어가 결코 아닙니다. 어떤 의미에서는 컴퓨터 과학 자체만큼 오래된 것입니다.
here's a quote that i like very much on this topic instead of trying to produce a program to simulate the adult mind
성인의 마음을 시뮬레이션하는 프로그램을 만드는 대신 이 주제에 대해 제가 아주 좋아하는 인용문이 있습니다.
why not rather try to produce one which simulates the child's if this were then subjected to an appropriate course of education one would obtain the adult brain
적절한 교육 과정을 거치면 성인의 두뇌를 얻을 수 있는 어린이를 시뮬레이션하는 것을 제작하려고 하지 않는 이유는 무엇입니까?
who wrote this
누가 이 글을 썼냐고요?
Alan Turing
앨런 튜링